A Finding Aid to the Holger Cahill Papers, 1910-1993, bulk 1910-1960, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Writings, Lectures and Speeches, 1916-1960; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 14-15, 18
  - Typescripts For Art For The Millions, 1936-1940; 4.5; Archival Resource Key
    - Parr, Russell C., Reaching for Art, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0260-0265)
    - Quirt, Walter, On Mural Painting, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0266-0269)
    - Rackley, Mildred, The United American Artists, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0270-0281)
    - Richardson, Antonio, [ Social Function of Art - It's Relation to the Public], circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0282-0290)
    - Rothschild, Lincoln, The Artist and Democracy, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0291-0296)
    - Seltzner, Leo, On the Making of the Film "The Technique of Fresco Painting,", circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0297-0299)
    - Smith, David, Modern Sculpture and Society, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0300-0308)
    - Smith, E. Herndon, The Organization of Supervisors of the Federal Art Project, circa 1937-1940; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0310-0313)
    - Speck, Walter E., Pottery Methods, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0314-0318)
    - Stavenitz, Alexander R., The Therapy of Art, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0320-0336)
    - Sutton, Harry H., High Noon in Art, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0337-0363)
    - Thorp, George, The Art of Supervising Artists, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0364-0368)
    - Trentham, Eugene, Golden Colorado, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0369-0372)
    - Ward, Lynd, Printmakers to the American People, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0373-0377)
    - Weisenborn, Rudolph, Designing a Diorama for the T.V.A., 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0378-0382)
    - White, Francis Robert, Cultural Frontiers, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0383-0389)
    - Wolff, Robert Jay, Chicago and the Artists' Union, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0390-0402)
    - Unidentified Author, The Artists as a Social Worker, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 211)
- Minutes of Meetings and Panel Discussions, Non-FAP, 1939-1947; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Box 15
  This series documents the proceedings of meetings of the American Handicraft Council, the Arts and Letters Secretariat, the Artists' International Association, and a Conference on the Support of the Visual Arts. There is also a typescript of an American Federation of Arts annual convention panel with notes on Cahill's presentation as part of that panel. Material is arranged in chronological order.
  - American Handicraft Council By-Laws and Meeting Minutes (April 19, 1939, December 20, 1939), Archival Resource Key (Reel 5288, Frame 0027-0047)
  - Typescript of the American Federation of Arts panel, "How Can We Support an American Art?,", March 18, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0460-0516)
  - Arts and Letters Secretariat Meeting, December 5, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5288, Frame 0065-0071)
  - Artists' International Association meeting, "International Co-operation Between Artists," Czechoslovakian Institute, April 22, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5288, Frame 0072-0080)
  - Conference on the Support of the Visual Arts, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Boston, Massachusetts, February 14-15, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5288, Frame 0081-0089)
- Notes and Research Material, 1935-1970; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.25 Linear feet Boxes 15-16
  This series contains research material on folk art and folk artists in addition to material that appears to be related to Cahill's criticism of William Francis McDonald's book Federal Relief Administration and the Arts (Ohio State University Press, 1969) sponsored by the American Council of Learned Societies.
  Notes found here are primarily for The Artists' America, an unpublished book by Cahill, and include typescripts of essay fragments and artist biographies, and lists of artists and works of art showing locations and owners. There are also notes relating to the review of the book The Birth of the American Tradition in Art, by Oskar Hagen, handwritten notes relating to Erwin Panofsky and miscellaneous notes.
  - American Council of Learned Societies, circa 1949; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0519-0531)
  - Erwin Panofsky, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0533-0581)
  - Folk Art and Folk Art Dealers, 1935, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0583-0670)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 1105, Frame 0347-0364)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1935-1970; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 1317-1435)
  - Notes for The Artists' America, circa 1941-1946; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0959-1315)
  - Notes for Book Review, The Birth of the American Tradition, by Unidentified Author for The New Republic, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0953-0958)
- Artwork, undated; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Boxes 16, 18
  Artwork in this series consists of four undated drawings of animals by Walt Speck, an undated pen and ink drawing by an unidentified artist of an artist sketching in front of a house, and an undated drawing and a lithograph by unidentified artists.
  - Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 1436-1445)
- Printed Material, 1910-1985; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 16-17
  This series consists of news clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, prospectuses, calendars of events, programs, brochures, booklets, books, government publications and reproductions of artwork. Much of the material dated between 1935 and 1943 relates to the WPA FAP. News clippings contain copies of approximately thirty articles, including book reviews, written by Cahill for a variety of publications between 1921 and 1960. Some of the material contains hand-written notes.
  - Brochures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0325-0345)
  - Booklets, 1925-1941; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0347-0431)
  - Books, Federal Sponsored Community Art Centers, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0434-0490)
  - Books, American Painting, by Holger Cahill, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0492-0506)
  - Books, George O. "Pop" Hart, Edited with Introduction by Holger Cahill, 1928; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0508-0550)
  - Books, Primitives: Poems and Woodcuts, by Max Weber, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0552-0572)
  - Books, The Arts of Painting and Sculpture, by Roger Fry, 1932; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0574-0579)
  - Books, Work For Artists: What? Where? How?, Edited by Elizabeth McCausland, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0581-0688)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1935-1943; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0567-0665)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1922-1929; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0666-0725)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930-1933; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0726-0757)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0758-0808)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0809-0828)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0829-0956)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0957-1043)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, January-April 1938; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 1044-1099)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, May-July 1938; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 1100-1125)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, August-December 1938; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 1126-1149)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, January-March 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 1150-1197)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, April-August 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 1198-1240)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, September 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 1241-1300)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, October-December 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0004-0034)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0035-0087)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1941-1947; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0088-0140)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1952-1967; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0141-0160)
  - Government Publications, 1933-1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0690-0725)
  - Government Publications, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0727-0745)
  - Government Publications, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0813-0815)
  - Government Publications, 1942-1943; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0864-0909)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0959-0966)
  - News Clippings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 0800-0904)
  - News Clippings, 1910, 1918-1919; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 0905a-0905r)
  - News Clippings, 1920-1922; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 0905s-0945)
  - News Clippings, 1923-1929; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 0947-0987)
  - News Clippings, 1930-1931; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 0988-1012)
  - News Clippings, 1932; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1013-1051)
  - News Clippings, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1052-1083)
  - News Clippings, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1084-1122)
  - News Clippings, 1935; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1123-1145)
  - News Clippings, January-October 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1147-1189)
  - News Clippings, October 1-3, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1190-1205)
  - News Clippings, October 4-8, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1206-1225)
  - News Clippings, October 9-13, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1226-1245)
  - News Clippings, October 14-17, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1246-1261)
  - News Clippings, October 18-31, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1262-1277)
  - News Clippings, November-December 1936; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1278-1279)
  - News Clippings, January-April 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1280-1298)
  - News Clippings, May-August 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1299-1315)
  - News Clippings, September-December 1937; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1316-1353)
  - News Clippings, January-August 1938; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1354-1394)
  - News Clippings, September-October 1938; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5294, Frame 1396-1421)
  - News Clippings, October-December 1938; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0003-0023)
  - News Clippings, January-May 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0024-0061)
  - News Clippings, June-August 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0062-0079)
  - News Clippings, September-December 1939; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0080-0098)
  - News Clippings, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0099-0135)
  - News Clippings, January-June 1941; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0136-0164)
  - News Clippings, July-December 1941; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0165-0188)
  - News Clippings, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0189-0259)
  - News Clippings, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0260-0276)
  - News Clippings, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0277-0308)
  - News Clippings, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0309-0324)
  - News Clippings, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0326-0372)
  - News Clippings, 1947-1949; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0373-0403)
  - News Clippings, 1950-1953; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0404-0441)
  - News Clippings, 1954-1955; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0442-0470)
  - News Clippings, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0471-0506)
  - News Clippings, 1957-1959; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0507-0512)
  - News Clippings, 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0513-0549)
  - News Clippings, 1970-1985; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5295, Frame 0550-0564)
  - Picture Postcards (blank), undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0931-0958)
  - Press Releases (1 of 2), undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0163-0169)
  - Press releases (2 of 2), undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0175-0181)
  - Press releases, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0170-0171)
  - Press releases, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0172-0174)
  - Press releases, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0182-0210)
  - Press releases, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0211-0214)
  - Programs and Calendars of Events, 1935-1945; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0242-0323)
  - Programs and Calendars of Events, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5292, Frame 0442-0459)
  - Prospectuses, 1934-circa 1941; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0217-0239)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, 1939, undated; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0911-0928)
- Photographs, circa 1917-1960; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders Box 17
  This series contains photographs of Cahill and family and colleagues including his mother and sister, Harry Hopkins, Edward Rowan, Eleanor Roosevelt and attendees of an FAP meeting including Stanton MacDonald-Wright. Also found here are photographs of miscellanous artwork. For WPA FAP photographs see 3.14: Photographs.
  - Photographs of Cahill with Family and Colleagues, circa 1917-circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5296, Frame 0968-1018)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Artwork, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Reel 5299, Frame 1126-1155)